<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loyalty of the last Long Parliament, or, A letter to an English gentlemen at Florence shewing that the late Parliements address'd against did not so much intrench on the prerogative as that of XVIII years continuance, of whom His Majesty said "never any king was so happy in a House of Commons as I in this," King's Answer, 20 Febr. 1663.</title>
            <author>T. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13684402</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13684402</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27382)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 833:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loyalty of the last Long Parliament, or, A letter to an English gentlemen at Florence shewing that the late Parliements address'd against did not so much intrench on the prerogative as that of XVIII years continuance, of whom His Majesty said "never any king was so happy in a House of Commons as I in this," King's Answer, 20 Febr. 1663.</title>
                  <author>T. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith, Senior,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: T.B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101338:1"/>
            <p> THE LOYALTY OF THE LAST <hi>Long Parliament:</hi> OR, A LETTER TO AN <hi>Engliſh Gentleman</hi> AT FLORENCE.</p>
            <p>SHEWING, That the late Parliaments <hi>(Addreſs'd againſt)</hi> did not ſo much Intrench on the PREROGATIVE, as that of XVIII YEARS Continuance, of whom His Majeſty ſaid, <hi>NEVER any KING was ſo happy in a</hi> Houſe <hi>of</hi> Commons, <hi>as I in this.—</hi>King's ANSWER, 20 <hi>Febr.</hi> 1663.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> Senior. 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101338:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101338:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE LOYALTY OF THE LAST <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> And their APPROVERS; <hi>In a LETTER to an Engliſh Gentleman at</hi> Florence.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received yours of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1. <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> wherein you are pleaſed to diſcover to me your <hi>Sentiments</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſtate of the Parties among us, and the diviſion of Minds about publick Affairs; whence I readily perceive how obnoxious you that live in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Countries, are to Miſ-informations and Falſe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of the ſtate of your own Country: For whilſt you take your Meaſures either from publick Prints, or private Letters, written either by the <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Yorkian</hi> Party, (and ſuch are all that are brought over and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd by the Men of <hi>Intelligence</hi> where you are;) You are altogether as unable to give a right Judgment, as he that determines a Cauſe having heard only one Party.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, you imagine that we here are now again divided in our Minds and Actings relating to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, juſt as we were forty years ago, and that they are the ſame Men, or thoſe that ſucceed in the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that are now proſecuting the ſame Ends, even the alteration of Government both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and inſtead of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Monarchy,</hi> to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101338:3"/> 
               <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>Democracy.</hi> Indeed it cannot be wonder'd that you who have liv'd ſo many years out of your own Country amongſt ſtrangers, ſhould harbour ſuch conceits, when even here (where men have ſuch plentiful means of true Information) the <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Mercenary Agents</hi> working upon Prejudice in ſome, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Envy and Revenge in others; Jealouſie in one ſort, and affectation of Prudence in another: Prevail with many to forget <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters, Sir <hi>Edmund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey</hi>'s Murder, and the Tryal of my Lord <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> much more the dreadful Burning of <hi>London;</hi> the the two Armies, one of 73, the other of 78. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> the Popiſh Deſigns of <hi>Clifford,</hi> the Impeachment of <hi>Danby,</hi> and the Popiſh Lords by divers Parliaments; the many Sham-plots, eſpecially that diſcover'd by <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> or the Meal-tub Plot; the Subornation of Witneſſes to take away the Life of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> by odious Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations; the Aſſaſſination of Juſtice <hi>Arnold,</hi> and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to corrupt <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and others: not to ſpeak of the Tryal and Judgment given and executed upon <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and upon <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Murderers, and upon the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits;</hi> and many other things, which demonſtratively prove the Plot of introducing Popery and Slavery into theſe Nations, or in <hi>Coleman</hi>'s own phraſe, <hi>Of utter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing a peſtilent Hereſie, &amp;c.</hi> And according to my Lord <hi>D.</hi> of Governing without a Parliament. It cannot be wonder'd at, I ſay, that ſuch as you ſhould falſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the State of theſe Kingdoms: But if you will have the patience to look a little back upon ſome few things that are paſt, and compare them with things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, you will eaſily perceive that it is not ſome factious men of Commonwealth Principles, nor the Clamours of Non-conformiſts againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrarineſs,</hi> that forms the diſcontented and agrieved People among
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101338:3"/> us, but it is in truth the old and loyal Friends of the <hi>KING, RELIGION</hi> and <hi>GOVERNMENT</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> ſuch as aſſiſted His Majeſty and his Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their Wars and Councels, and the Succeſſors and Adherents of ſuch who conſtitute the Bulk of the ſubſtantial Men and Proteſtants in the Nation, with whom the Diſſenters joyn and fall in. Theſe are the men who for theſe nine or ten years laſt paſt, have ſeen and ſet themſelves againſt the <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Deſigns carried on by Cabal Councels and Paraſites. Indeed the Diſcovery of the horrid <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> and <hi>Treaſons</hi> did open the eyes of many, who would not ſee theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Deſigns till they had a Meridian Light.</p>
            <p>That this is the <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> will appear plainly to you, if you conſider, with what earneſt deſire, joy and applauſe, His Majeſtry was reſtored to his Crown; was ever any people ſo tranſported with Joy and Triumph as the people of <hi>England?</hi> Inſomuch, that even thoſe who where obnoxious to, and ſuffered Capital Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments afterwards, were lull'd into a hope of Impunity by the univerſal Congratulation. Then as ſoon as might be, was the King's <hi>Long Parliament</hi> call'd, whilſt the people was in this paſſion, and they choſe (to be ſure) thoſe eſpecially whom they apprehended moſt grateful to the King and his Prerogative, and moſt averſe to the Principles and Practices of foregoing times. This appear'd in all the Votes, Addreſſes, and Bills of that Parliament for many years; wherein they ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all their skill to aſſert the King's Power and Authority againſt Parliamentary Pretenſions, and had almoſt rais'd his Revenue to ſuch a prodigious height, that he ſhould never need Supplies from his People. They were ſo fully addicted to pleaſe the King, that he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 20 <hi>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1663.</note> ſays, <hi>Never any King was ſo happy in a Houſe of Commons, as He in this.</hi> And ſurely he judg'd aright concerning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101338:4"/> them, if the King's happineſs conſiſt in the Parliaments Concurrence with Cabinet Dictates.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the Gentlemen of this Houſe began, after the dreadful Burning of <hi>London,</hi> (which to a Committee of their Houſe was prov'd by many ſhrewd Evidences, to be done by contrivance of the <hi>Papiſts)</hi> to make Addreſſes againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to repreſs their Inſolencies. But in the Year 1672, after the Plotters had procur'd the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to be ſhut up, and the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of many Thouſands of the People in it, and that the <hi>Tripple League</hi> (which coſt the people ſo great Sums of Money in favour of it) was diſſolv'd, and a War againſt <hi>Holland</hi> in Conjunction with <hi>France</hi> was commenc'd; and the penal Laws againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penc'd with by Declaration: the Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſaw clearly which way they were driving, and therefore as ſoon as they were permitted to ſit, Addreſt the King againſt that Declaration of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Him, <hi>That penal Statutes in matters Eccleſiaſtical, cannot be ſuſpended but by Act of Parliament.</hi> And though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>br.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>672.</note> His Majeſty tell them in anſwer, <hi>That they queſtion His Power in Eccleſiaſticks, which he finds not done in the Reign of any of his Anceſtors:</hi> Yet they reply, <hi>That his Majeſty hath been very much miſinformed, ſince no ſuch Power was ever claim'd or exercis'd by any of his Predeceſſors.</hi> In fine, His Majeſty was induced to cancel that Declaration, and declare it ſhould be no Preſident for the future.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I would gladly ask our Boaſters of Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Exclaimers againſt the late Parliaments, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting open and ſecret <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for whoſe Intereſt this Indulgence was procur'd) whether they approv'd of what the King did, or of what the Parliament did in this Affair. If of the Declaration, then they had the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in Generall on their ſides, owning the Prerogative by taking Licences for exerciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101338:4"/> Worſhip and Religion contrary to Law: if they did not approve of the Declaration, but of the Addreſs, then let them acknowledge that at this turn, the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> were more Loyall (as they call it) and greater Adorers of Prerogative then themſelves, and that it is not the King's Prerogative which theſe love, but their own Malignity, and the Prerogative for the ſake of that; ſo that if the King ſhould uſe his Prerogative contrary to their minds, they would be as much againſt it as now they are for it: Judge they as they will concerning it, it's a plain Caſe, that the Parliament, which ſprang out of the moſt Ardent Affection that ever was in a People towards their Prince, and out of the greateſt Deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Republican Principles, yet reſolv'd that the King was deceiv'd by his Cabal Councillors in a matter, which in the direct conſequence of it <hi>tended to the interrupting the free courſe of the Laws, and altering the Legiſlative Power.</hi> And ſince the diſcovery of <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters, I think there's none doubts but that Indulgence was the effect of Popiſh Councils; and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who deſigned the greateſt advantage to their cauſe by it, If any Favour was intended for <hi>Diſſenters</hi> by it, it's ſtrange that His Majeſty ſhould not paſs a Bill for Nulling of the Rigorous Act of the thirty five of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when it had already paſt both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Seſſion of Parliament it was, that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament paſſ'd a Bill for impoſing a Teſt againſt Popery upon all that ſhould bear any Office Civil or Military in the Kingdom, which the Duke of <hi>York</hi> ſubmitting to, had his Commiſſion of High Admiral vacated, but his Advice and Influence ſtill vigorous. By this means al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo my Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> was diſcover'd to be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and quitted his High Office of Lord Treaſurer and great Miniſter of State. Was it not high time for thoſe in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101338:5"/> Parliament that had any love to their Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to look about 'em? Or was it ſawcily done for the Parliament to concern themſelves with the King's Councellors, and find fault with their manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Nay, they proceeded ſo far in the next Seſſion, as to Addreſs againſt the conſummation of the Marriage between his Royal Highneſs and the Dutches of <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> (which was already done by Proxy) becauſe ſhe was a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> And after they had receiv'd one Anſwer from his Majeſty in this matter, The Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament proceed to give their reaſons againſt it, <hi>praying him to relieve his Subjects from thoſe fears and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which at preſent they lie under, from the Progreſs made in that Treaty—That for another Age at the leaſt, this Kingdom will be under continual Apprehenſions of the GROWTH of POPERY. And the danger of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Octo.</hi> 31. 1673.</note> 
               <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Here we ſee that the language of fears and apprehenſions of the <hi>Growth of Popery,</hi> and danger of Proteſtantiſm, is as well the language of the King's happieſt Parliament, that ever was, as of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happieſt Parliament of Forty One.</p>
            <p>Three days after this, they Addreſs to his Majeſty for a General Faſt, and that upon theſe Grounds, (viz.) <hi>Being paſſionately ſenſible of the Calamitous condition of this Kingdom, not only by reaſon of the War (which was then mannaged againſt the</hi> Dutch) <hi>wherein it is at preſent involved, but many other intestine differences and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongst us, which are chiefly occaſioned by the undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning contrivances of Popiſh Recuſants, whoſe numbers and inſolencies are greatly of late increaſed, and whoſe reſtleſs practiſes threaten a</hi> Subverſion <hi>both of Church and State.</hi> What is the difference now between this Seventy Three Parliament, and that of Forty One.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feb.</hi> 7. Following, they ſhew there reſentment of the <hi>Black-heath</hi> Army, and reſolve, <hi>That the continuing of</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101338:5"/> 
               <hi>any ſtanding forces in this Nation, other than the</hi> Militia, <hi>is a great grievance and vexation to the People.</hi> What? This Loyal Parliament talk of grievances and vexation to the People in the King's management of his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>This Houſe of Commons (as well as ſome that have been ſince) take upon them to pray the King to remove ſome of his Great Councellors from his Preſence and their Publick Imployments. But their Addreſs againſt Duke <hi>Lauderdale, Feb.</hi> 23. 75. is very remarkable, both for the matter and language of it; for thus they ſay<hi>—Though we have great cauſe to reſt aſſured of the continuance of your Majeſties Gracious Diſpoſition towards us, yet we find upon a ſerious examination of the State of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that there is a great jealouſie ariſen from ſome State-proceedings in the Hearts of your Subjects; That ſome Perſons in great imployment under your Majeſty have fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented deſigns, contrary to the Intereſt of your Majeſty and People, intending to deprive us of our antient Rights and Liberties, that thereby they might the more eaſily introduce the Popiſh Religion, and an ARBITRARY Form of GOVERNMENT, to the Ruine and Deſtruction of the whole Kingdom.</hi> Here's a Charge with a Witneſs: all the worſt of Forty one Forms of Declaiming againſt the Government. This is the Generall Charge; let's hear the Particular<hi>—The ſaid Duke of</hi> Lauderdale <hi>did Publickly affirm in the Preſence of your Majeſty ſitting in Council; And before divers of your Majesties Subjects then attending, that your Majeſties Edicts ought to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for your Majeſties Edicts are equal with Laws, and ought to be obſerved in the firſt place. Thereby juſtifying the ſaid Declaration</hi> [of 15 March, 71.] <hi>and the proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and declaring his Inclinations to</hi> Arbitrary Councels, <hi>in terrour of your Majeſties good Subjects.</hi> They conclude thus; <hi>We do therefore in all humility implore your Sacred</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101338:6"/> 
               <hi>Majeſty—That for the eaſe of the hearts of your people, who are poſſeſt with extream grief and ſorrow to ſee your Majeſty thus AB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SED, and the Kingdom endangered; That your Majeſty would graciouſly be pleaſed to remove the ſaid Duke of</hi> Lauderdale <hi>from all his Imployments, &amp;c.</hi> Is not this Writing after the 41 Copy? Is not this ſtriking at His Majeſty and the Government through his Miniſters ſides? What! that Houſe of Commons tell His Majeſty he is <hi>abuſed,</hi> and the Kingdom <hi>endanger'd,</hi> which was choſen, and nouriſh'd, and indulg'd for 18 years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be an enſample to all ſucceeding Parliaments.</p>
            <p>But to proceed in His Majeſties Anſwer to their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the 20, or 26th of <hi>May,</hi> 77. adviſing him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a <hi>League Offenſive</hi> and <hi>Defenſive</hi> with the <hi>States</hi> againſt <hi>France:</hi> He tells them, <hi>How highly he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at that great invaſion of his Prerogative.</hi> And in His Majeſties Anſwer to their Addreſs of <hi>Jan.</hi> 31, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minds them of it: <hi>But</hi> (ſays He) <hi>you take no notice of it, but on the contrary, add to your former ill Conduct, new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions equally offenſive to His Majeſties Authority, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to His (and He thinks) moſt other mens judgments.</hi> Unhappy Houſe of Commons now, how ever happy heretofore, thus to interfere with His Maieſties Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Judgment too.</p>
            <p>This ſharp <hi>Anſwer</hi> and <hi>Reproof</hi> bears date 4th of <hi>Febr.</hi> 77. but in <hi>March</hi> following the Parliament having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd a Poll-Bill for furniſhing His Majeſty with money, for entring into an actual War againſt the <hi>French King,</hi> His Majeſty paſt that Bill, <hi>March</hi> 20. Thus with great vigour and animoſity, to the univerſal joy of the whole Nation, Drums were beat up, and all preparations made for the War, and a bitter Book, intituled, <hi>Chriſtianiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus chriſtianandus,</hi> publiſhed by Allowance, againſt the <hi>French;</hi> but the Conſpiritors at Court intended no ſuch thing, for the then Lord Treaſurer's Letter to Mr. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101338:6"/> then Ambaſſador in the <hi>French</hi> Court, bares date 5 daies after, <hi>viz. Mar.</hi> 25. wherein he gives him directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for propoſing Conditions of Peace between the King and ours with the Confederates, and ſuch as for which (ſays he) <hi>the King expects to have ſix Millions of Livers yearly for three years—becauſe</hi> (he adds) <hi>it will be two or three years before he can hope to find his Parliament in humour to give him ſupplies, after the having made any Peace with</hi> France. This I take notice of, to let you ſee, Sir, how different Sentiments and Deſigns that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Parliament and the great Miniſters had in the tranſacting of State-matters. But before this Letter was diſcover'd, the Commons in their Addreſs of <hi>May,</hi> 10, 78. did deeply reſent the Councils the King took in theſe Affairs. <q rend="margQuotes">'For they tell his Majeſty, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing of their advice [given the 26 of <hi>May</hi> before, and reiterated the 31 of <hi>January</hi> enſuing] and diſmiſſing the Parliament in <hi>May</hi> laſt, was the accaſion of theſe ill Conſequences, which have ſince ſucceeded both at home and abroad. All which have ariſen from thoſe miſrepreſentations (ſay they) of our proceedingss which have been ſuggeſted to your Majeſty by ſome particular perſons in a Clandeſtine way, without the Participation and Advice, as we conceive, of your Council-board, as though we had invaded upon your Majeſties Prerogative of making Peace and War: Whereas we did only, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon which Grounds your Majeſty was induced to give us ſuch Anſwers, to thoſe two Addreſſes rejecting our advice, as thereby your Majeſties good Subjects have been infinitely diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the State of your Majeſties Affairs reduced to a moſt <hi>deplorable</hi> condition. We do therefore moſt humbly deſire, that for the good and ſafety of this Kingdom and the ſatisfaction of your Subjects, your Majeſty would Graciouſly be pleaſed to remove thoſe Councellors, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101338:7"/>
            <p> Theſe things were done and ſaid by this Parliament, even before the diſcovery of the horrid Popiſh Plot, and Treaſons. For how vigorouſly they acted after that diſcovery in the Proſecution of <hi>Coleman,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Godfrey</hi>'s Murderers, in the Impeachment of the Popiſh Lords and <hi>Danby,</hi> for High Treaſon, in throwing out the Popiſh Lords from ſitting in the Lords Houſe, and other matters, (for which they were ſubjected to an Honourable Death or Diſſolution) I ſhall not need to mention, becauſe they are freſh in every ones memory: One thing of an elder date I will call to mind, wherein the temper of that Houſe againſt Popiſh and Arbitrary deſigns, does notably appear it was their rejecting of two Bills paſt in the Houſe of Lords, and ſent down to the Commons, The one was tituled, <hi>An Act for the more effectual Conviction and Proſecution of Popiſh Recuſants;</hi> which they rejected with great contempt, for being ready to put the queſtion for throwing it out, it was mov'd they ſhould ſtop a while to ſee if any Member of their Houſe had the face to ſpeak for it. It appearing ſo evidently to them that this Bill tended directly contrary to its Title. The other Bill was to be <hi>An Act for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecuring of the Proteſtant Religion, by Educating the Children of the Royal Family therein, and for the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the continuance of a Proteſtant Clergy.</hi> In this Bill there was a Teſt to be preſented to every future King and Queen of this Realm againſt Popery. A fine Project, which clearly implied, that any King or Queen in future may be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and then the ſecurity of the Proteſtant Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was to lye in this <hi>Paper-Statute,</hi> Maugre all the Wit, Policy, Craft, Power, ſecret and open violence of all <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> with the Crown of <hi>England</hi> on their ſides. But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons rejecting this, did not only ſhew diſaffection to Popiſh Cabal Councils, but alſo their judgment in ſeeing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101338:7"/> into the malice of thoſe contrivancies, that had already over reach'd the Houſe of Peers with the Biſhops in it, and that in the great concern of Religion their proper Province.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Impeachment of the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> is a full diſcovery of the ſence of that Houſe touching Court Councils and Actions, give me leave to mind you of it more particularly.</p>
            <p n="1">The firſt Article ſaith, <hi>That he hath Trayterouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croacht to himſelf Royal Power, by treating in matters of Peace and War with Forraign Ministers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>againſt the Expreſs Declaration of His Majeſty and His Parliament, &amp;c.</hi> For when the King at the inſtance of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had made proviſion for War, had raiſed an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and money for that end. Then did he treat of peace with the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, and with the <hi>French</hi> King by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſſador, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="2">The ſecond Article, <hi>That he hath Trayterouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to</hi> ſubvert <hi>the antient and well eſtabliſht Form of Government in this Kingdom, and inſtead thereof to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an Arbitrary and Tyrannical way of Government, and the better to effect this His purpoſe he did deſign the raiſing of an Army, upon pretence of a War againſt the</hi> French <hi>King; and to continue the ſame as a ſtanding Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Kingdom:</hi> And miſ-imployed the money given for the disbanding of that Army to the continuance of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Article, <hi>That he Traiterouſly intending to hinder the Meetings of Parliaments, and to deprive His Majeſty of their Council, and thereby to alter the conſtitution of the Government, did negotiate a Peace for the</hi> French <hi>King—for the doing whereof he endeavoured to procure a great ſumm of money of him; for the carrying on his Trayterous deſigns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Article, <hi>That he is Popiſhly affected, and hath Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101338:8"/> 
               <hi>concealed the late horrid Popiſh Plot—and hath ſuppreſt the Evidence, and reproachfully diſcountenanc'd the Kings Witneſſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Article, <hi>That he hath waſted the Kings Treaſure, by iſſuing out of His Majeſties</hi> Exchequer<hi>—for unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Penſions and ſecret ſervices, to the value of</hi> 231602. l. <hi>within two years,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Article, <hi>That he hath by indirect means procured from His Majeſty to himſelf, divers conſiderable Gifts and Grants of Inheritance of the antient Revenue of the Crown, even contrary to Acts of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have a great Favorite, and mighty Miniſter of State accuſed for High Treaſon, in reſpect of great Tranſactions of Government for a long time together: And the accuſed perſon thought not fit to ſtand upon his juſtification, and put himſelf upon his Tryal, but pleads his Majeſties pardon, thereby implicitely confeſſing his guilt. And that is of the higheſt nature that can be, no leſs then ſubverting the antient and well eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Form of Government in this Kingdom, and introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing an Arbitrary and Tyranical way of Government.</p>
            <p>But that which is more to my purpoſe is, the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the perſons that exhibit this charge, I have told you already who they were, ſuch a Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, ſo Loyal, ſo oblig'd in Intereſt and Affections to Prerogative, ſo abominating all Principles and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences againſt it, or that may ſeek to intrench upon it, as never can a better on that account be expected in <hi>England;</hi> now if this Houſe find ſuch horrid Crimes in Court-councellors. And if the three Parliaments we have had ſince, have but proceeded in the ſame Methods which this Parliament took, and led them into, then the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from theſe Premiſes are very Obvious; as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Court is in the Opinion of the Kings beſt Subjects and Friends liable to be abus'd by not only ill
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101338:8"/> and hurtfull, but by treaſonous, and deſtructive Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That (which is the thing I under took to ſhew you) not only the beſt, the wiſeſt, the loyaleſt, but the Body of the Nation is of this mind, and will ever be ſo, as there is great reaſon to conclude.</p>
            <p n="3">3, That they who would perſwade His Majeſty and the People, that the actions of the late Parliament which are but the ſame, or of the very ſame Nature with thoſe of this Long Parliament are irrugelar, factious, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, injurious to the Kings Prerogative and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, do in plain conſequence find fault with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Government and legiſlative Power of <hi>England,</hi> by King, Lords and Commons, and deſire and endeavour the ſubverting of it.</p>
            <p>That the Body of the People, the loyaleſt, and moſt ſubſtantial part of the Nation is thus minded and will in reaſon alwaies be ſo, appears from the Nature of the Long Parliament and the continuance of it, and the Succeſſors of it. For that Parliament continued about 18 years, and we have had three ſince in theſe 3 years, and all agreeing in the ſame Councels, in oppoſition to Court Councels and actings. Now if the People can never be expected in any circumſtances, to be better inclin'd to chuſe a Prerogative Parliament than they were at the choice of that, and that the Parliaments ſince have been of the ſame temper and judgment, and this for 21 years, 3 lives of ſingle perſons, how can it be imagin'd we ſhould ever have a more Prerogative Parliament. And then my third Inference follows, that they who Inveigh againſt theſe Parliaments, do in true conſtruction inveigh againſt the conſtitution of Parliaments in <hi>England,</hi> and deſires the Subverſion of the Government. For if all the Individuals be naught the Species muſt needs be naught, which ſubſiſts in theſe Individuals. If all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101338:9"/> Parliaments that have been theſe threeſcore years have been in theſe mens Opinion ſeditious and injurious to the Kings Rights, and are ever like to be ſo, ſurely there ought to be a Reformation, for injury ought not to be done to the Kings Rights, and there remains no way to remedy this but the alteration of the antient <hi>Engliſh</hi> conſtitution, and either to throw off Parliaments wholly, or to reduce them to the preſent State of the <hi>French</hi> Parliaments, that they may not dare to oppoſe, or not to affirm and ratifie every of the Kings Edicts, or according to the <hi>Scoth</hi> Oracle, Duke <hi>Lauderdale, That the Kings Edicts are not only equal to Laws, but ought to be obeyed in the firſt place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I hope Sir, you cannot imagine that the Body of the People can be weary of their Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or that any but ſuch as I ſpoke of at firſt, perſons obxnoious to the Juſtice of Parliaments, their Friends and Favourers, Deputies, the envious and revengeful <hi>Papists,</hi> or indifferent to any Religion, or thoſe that hate all that are not of their minds, or whoſe Intereſt it is to deſire a <hi>French</hi> Government, together with ſome dull Spirits that think it the only way to peace and quietneſs, yield up all to Court-councels of what kind ſo ever; ſuch as theſe are the Party, the Faction, the Clamorers againſt the late Parliaments, and in them againſt all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Here, Sir, I that to have concluded, having in my Opinion ſaid enough to ſhew that the preſent Lovers of Parliament Councels, are both the greateſt part or body of the Kingdom (which appears from their choice of Repreſentatives, for the Commons in Parliament do beſt ſpeak the Voice of the people) and alſo the moſt loyal and true Lovers of His Majeſty and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, but I crave your leave to add ſome more things that occur to my mind in reference to this matter.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101338:9"/>
            <p> And you may remember (if at leaſt you were then in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land)</hi> that in the Year 75. there was a great Conteſt between the Lords Houſe and the Houſe of Commons, about Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, inſomuch that the Lords enter'd into a Debate, and put the Queſtion, Whether they ſhould Petition His Majeſty to diſſolve that Parliament and call a new one, which had been carried in the Affirmative, if they had decided it by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of Lords, then preſent at the Debate; but they but they call'd in the Aid of Voices by <hi>Proxy,</hi> and ſo conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it Negatively: thereupon the affirming Lords make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt it, and give their Reaſons; which Reaſons and many other Objections againſt the continuance of that Parliament, were anſwered in a <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> intituled, <hi>A Packet of Advices to the Men of</hi> Shaftsbury: which tho' it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a mercenary Pen, yet there's no doubt (that I ever heard) of it's being written at the Inſtigation of the then <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> and contains as high praiſes of that Parliament as can be given; I'le inſtance but in one or two paſſages, <hi>pa.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Parliament</hi> (ſaith that Author) <hi>which hath had the honour to re-ſettle the Crown and Kingdom, after it had, by a wonderful hand of God, been but newly reſcu'd out of the ruines of a late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; a</hi> Parliament <hi>that hath done perhaps more for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of this well-temper'd</hi> Monarchy, <hi>than many other of the beſt</hi> Parliaments <hi>put together ever did before: and I may boldly ſay, becauſe it can be prov'd by Inſtances of Fact, that they have done more towards the containing of</hi> Monarchy Power, <hi>in its juſt bounds, than any</hi> Parliament <hi>ever did, that may be counted to have been the moſt popular and publick hearted. And</hi> p. 56. <hi>the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of this</hi> Houſe of Commons <hi>are known to be men of the beſt Quality and of Eſtates, and of the beſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; they underſtand what the true Intereſt of the</hi> Crown <hi>is, and—as they have ever been, ſo they ſtill are right and firm to it and the Government.</hi> This was the Earl of <hi>D.</hi> judgment of this Houſe in thoſe days; but when they came to Impeach him of <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> then the dangers of Diſſolving them are quite blown away; and now it's adviſable, that His Majeſty
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101338:10"/> ſhould meet his People in frequent <hi>Parliaments.</hi> I would ask the Clamores againſt the late <hi>Parliaments,</hi> Whether they did not heartily approve of the Character given to that <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the Book cited, and of the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors Advice to continue it? If they did, how can they think that good Counſel which induced his Majeſty to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it; and that at a time when the people were never more full of Fears of the Deſigns of <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>King's Life,</hi> the Religion and Government of the Kingdom? Or was this Houſe of Parliament all of a ſuddain fallen from their Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, their Underſtanding and firmneſs to the Crown and Government? There was a long Bill of Penſioners ſaid to be found amongſt them, ſuch as the Treaſurer had gratified with the Sum of 231602 <hi>l.</hi> in two years time; I preſume theſe were not the cauſe of their Diſſolution: It was not the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers Intereſt to caſt of theſe Servants, whom he bought at of dear a rate. It was the generality of that Houſe which he had by his Agent ſo much extoll'd, whom he now falls out with, and by whoſe Influence, judge you, they were diſſolv'd! What clearer Demonſtration would any man have, that the <hi>Cabal Councellors,</hi> and the moſt ſubſtantial and loyal people of the Kingdom were now at odds: For to be ſure thoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Parliament which had behav'd themſelves well, and according to the minds of thoſe moſt loyal Freeholders, Citizens and Burgeſſers that choſe them at firſt, would be in high eſtates with them ſtill; and this they manifeſted by chooſing them into the Parliaments that ſucceeded. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we find near 200 beſides Court-dependants of the ſame individual men in the next Parliament. Thoſe that were left out, were either Penſioners or Dependants on <hi>Cabal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors:</hi> Thoſe that were choſen were the ableſt men of Parts and eſtates; whence it came to paſs, that theſe were the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-men ſtill in the Houſe of Commons, and thereforet read in the very ſame ſteps, and proſecuted the Treaſurer and his Adherents, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and their Abbetters, juſt as they had done before; with only this advantage, that they were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101338:10"/> freed from a heavy clog of Court-penſioners, where by they were more unanimous and more uniform in their Votes and Addreſſes, than they could be whilſt thoſe were among them.</p>
            <p>But we have a greater Teſtimony than this, that <hi>Cabal Councils</hi> and <hi>Parliament Councils</hi> were at a great diſtance; for His Majeſty himſelf in his <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>April</hi> 20. 79. whilſt this new Parliament was ſitting, for the diſſolution of his Old <hi>Privy Council,</hi> and the chooſing a new one, tells us, <hi>That He had been induc'd to uſe the Advices of ſome few—for many years paſt: He is ſorry for the ill ſucceſs he has found in this courſe, and ſenſible of the ill poſture of Affairs from that, and ſome unhappy Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which have raiſed great Jealouſies and Diſſatisfactions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his good Subjects, and thereby left the Crown and Government in a Condition too weak for thoſe Dangers we have reaſon to fear both at home and abroad.</hi> Hereupon he reſolves for the future to take the Advice of this <hi>Privy Council</hi> and the <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think this is an unexceptionable Evidence of the illneſs of <hi>Cabal Councellors,</hi> and the great difference between them and <hi>Parliaments:</hi> And I hope men ſhall not incur the reproach of <hi>Diſloyal, Fanatick, Whigs, Enemies to the King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</hi> for adhearing to, and commending the Counſels and Actions of Four <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſucceſſively, whereof the 18 years <hi>Parliament</hi> has ſuch Teſtimonies to their Ability and Loyalty, as they ſurpaſs in their opinion for any that has gone before them, or that in moral poſſibility can come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them; excepting thoſe that have already ſucceeded them, wherein their very ſelves made the moſt conſiderable and leading number: inſomuch that all theſe Four <hi>Parliaments</hi> may in reaſon be reckon'd One <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> with this difference, that in the Three laſt they were reform'd and purg'd from many diſeaſed and corrupt Members, which had been poyſon'd by <hi>Court Empericks:</hi> Shall men, I ſay, be made Enemies for adhering to this Houſe of Parliament, which repreſents both the Perſons, Judgments and Affections of all the ſubſtantial and unbyaſs'd Commons of <hi>England?</hi> And that againſt either the ſame Councellors, or thoſe that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101338:11"/> them in the ſame Spirit; eſpecially at the time, when the only ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and guilty <hi>Caballers,</hi> and the only hope they have of carrying on their Plots and Deſigns, lies in fomenting theſe Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and Animoſities among His Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects, and hindring the effectual ſitting of Parliaments: How many Sham-plots have they ſet on foot, to throw guilt upon theſe Proteſtants that are moſt eager in their Proſecution. How many perſons have they labour'd to Suborn to charge Treaſon, to take away at once the Lives and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of thoſe whoſe only ſecurity lies under Divine Providence, in the ſafety of the King and the Government, can you think Sir, that any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons can poſſibly be in theſe endeavours, and in that party but ſuch as I have already diſcribed unto you? You hear perhaps of many Addreſſes, which diſaprove of the late Parliament-councels and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and they are ſaid to come from numerous Bodies of men: But I conceive you will eaſily grant, that the temper of their Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves in Parliament doth better ſhew the temper of the People than thoſe Addreſſes, which many times are gained by ſiniſter Arts, and from a few that take upon them the Name of the Many.</p>
            <p>Beſides there is ſo much clear reaſon and wiſdom in the Houſe of Commons aſſembled in Councels, that even thoſe perſons that are choſen by the <hi>Caballers</hi> Intereſt, if at leaſt they have any ſparks of Ingenuity left in them, do ſometimes become quite other men, and have other Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents than they had before.</p>
            <p>Have we not known ſome, who by this change have reap'd the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Dam'ems of their Electors; ſo that the mind of the people can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be known till they meet together in Parliament. And I perſwade my ſelf that many of thoſe that are now of a contrary mind, could they but be admitted to hear the Debates in Parliament, would give their Suffrage to the ſame things they condemn. But I ſeem now to have ſaid enough in this matter, tho' very little to what might be ſaid, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all I have ſaid is plain matter of Fact: As for my reaſoning a little upon it, I refer it to your judgment whether it is not genuine and clear. But if you chance to ſhew my Letter to any of your <hi>Popiſh Converſants,</hi> they'l turn it off with a ſcoff, and think you muſt take that for an Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; but they are much miſtaken in you, or elſe I am, who ſtill retain that hearty affection for you, which I profeſt at your departure hence: and I am ſure I ſhall never ceaſe to love you, and hope I ſhall never have any cauſe not to Honour you for your Affection to all true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> and Lovers of <hi>Engliſh Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101338:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
